<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Computational Biology / Biological Computing</title>
    <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Computational Biology / Biological Computing</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://computingbiology.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Science Background</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/computer-science-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/computer-science-background/</guid>
      <description>Here is a guide to the computing background expected for students entering this course.
If you&amp;rsquo;ve completed cs2150 and a good Theory of Computation or Algorithms course (the official pre-requisites for this course) and remember the big ideas from that class, this should all be familiar to you already, but it may still be useful to refresh your understanding using these materials.
If you haven&amp;rsquo;t taken the prerequisite courses and are getting up to speed on your own, we hope these materials will be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cost of Computation</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/complexity/</guid>
      <description>When we consider the power of our computing models, we have been concerned with understanding what functions can be computed (in theory, which means without any arbitrary limits on their execution) by different computing models. When we want to actual compute using physical computers, cost matters.
For concerete computations where we already know the input and have an implementation of the algorithm, we can measure the cost of executing the algorithm by just running it and recording the cost.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Models of Computation</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/models/</guid>
      <description>To reason precisely about what computers can and cannot do, we need abstract models that capture the things we think are important but avoid the complexities of physical objects.
Models and Mathematics The physical world is messy and suffers from arbitrary limits — this applies both to the physical computing devices we use (which always have some probability of failing and can&amp;rsquo;t even do arithmetic correcly) and even more so to biological systems we consider in this class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/welcome/</guid>
      <description>This is the course website for &amp;ldquo;Computational Biology / Biological Computing&amp;rdquo;, a new University of Virginia course targeted to undergraduate computer science students that will be offered for the first time in Spring 2022. Scheduled course meetings are Mondays and Wednesday, 12:30pm – 1:45pm, in Olsson Hall 018, starting on 19 January 2022.
This course will look at connections between computing and biology, with a focus on DNA. It will include computational methods used in biology focusing on how computing can be used to analyze and design DNA, as well as opportunities to use biological substances and ideas to compute.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>