<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Computational Biology / Biological Computing</title>
    <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Computational Biology / Biological Computing</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://computingbiology.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 6</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/class5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/class5/</guid>
      <description>Schedule and Readings Due Tuesday, 8 February (4:59pm): Project 1
Before Wednesday, 9 February:
 Read Chapter 19 &amp;ndash; 26 of Hubert&amp;rsquo;s The DNA Book. (Chapter 26 on Mutations and Changes is the one most relevant to today&amp;rsquo;s class.) Read Chapter 5 of the Bioinformatics Algorithms: How do we compare biological sequences?.  Before Monday, 14 Feb:
 Chapter 26 of Manolis Kellis et al., Computational Biology - Genomes, Networks, and Evolution: Molecular Evolution and Phylogenetics (also available as [PDF])  Slides The slides from the 7 February class are here: class6.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 5</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/class5/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/class5/</guid>
      <description>Schedule and Readings Due Tuesday, 8 February (4:59pm): Project 1
Before Wednesday, 9 February:
 Read Chapter 19 &amp;ndash; 26 of Hubert&amp;rsquo;s The DNA Book. (Chapter 26 on Mutations and Changes is the one most relevant to today&amp;rsquo;s class.) Read Chapter 5 of the Bioinformatics Algorithms: How do we compare biological sequences?.  Slides The slides from 2 February class are here: class5.pdf
Some links to materials for the class:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 4</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/class4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/class4/</guid>
      <description>Schedule and Readings Due Tuesday, 8 February (4:59pm): Project 1
Before Wednesday, 9 February:
 Read Chapter 19 &amp;ndash; 26 of Hubert&amp;rsquo;s The DNA Book. (Chapter 19 is a bit different, but may be useful to give you ideas for the kinds of things you could do for the Final Project.) Read Chapter 5 of the Bioinformatics Algorithms: How do we compare biological sequences?.  Slides The slides from 31 January class are here: class4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 3</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/class3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/class3/</guid>
      <description>Schedule and Readings Before Monday, 31 January:
 Read Chapter 11 &amp;ndash; 18 of Hubert&amp;rsquo;s The DNA Book. Finish reading Chapter 3 (including 3.9) of the Bioinformatics Algorithms: How do we assemble genomes?.  Due Tuesday, 8 February (4:59pm): Project 1
Slides The slides from 26 January class are here: class3.pdf
   Some links to materials for the class:
  BRCA1 Patent: 17Q-linked breast and ovarian cancer susceptibility gene [PDF]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project 1: Assembling Genomes</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/project1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/project1/</guid>
      <description>Due: Tuesday, 8 February, 4:59pm To get started on Project 1, one of the team members should fork this github repo: https://github.com/computingbiology/Project-1-Genome-Assembly.
The file, project1.ipynb in the repository is a jupyter notebook that has the assignment and is where you will enter your answers.
You&amp;rsquo;ll be able to get started on the assignment by running: jupyter notebook project1.ipynb.
If you don&amp;rsquo;t have Jupyter installed, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to install this first: pip install jupyterlab or see https://jupyter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 2</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/class2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/class2/</guid>
      <description>Slides The slides from 24 January class are here: class2.pdf
Some links to materials for the class:
  J. D. Watson and F. H. C. Crick. Molecular Structure of Nucleic Acids: A Structure for Deoxyribose Nucleic Acid [PDF]. Nature, 25 April 1953. (Also read: Sexism in science: did Watson and Crick really steal Rosalind Franklin’s data?, The Guardian, 23 June 2015.)
  F. Sanger, S. Nicklen, and A. R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 1</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/week1/</guid>
      <description>Schedule and Readings Before 4:59pm Friday, 21 January:
 Join the Course Slack Read the Syllabus, Pledge, and complete the Registration Survey.  Before Monday&amp;rsquo;s class, 24 January:
  Read Chapters 1 &amp;ndash; 10 of Hubert&amp;rsquo;s The DNA Book (the chapters are very short, so its not as much as it sounds). To access the early version of this book that we have access to, you will need the account information that will be sent to the course slack.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Course Pledge</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/pledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/pledge/</guid>
      <description>Honor Expectations As a student at the University of Virginia, you are trusted to be honorable and expected to behave in ways that merit that trust. We take advantage of this trust to provide a better learning environment for everyone. In particular, students in this course are expected to follow these rules throughout the course:
I will not lie, cheat or steal. If I am unsure whether something would be considered lying, cheating or stealing, I will ask before doing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Course Registration Survey</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/survey/</guid>
      <description>Please submit this survey if you are enrolled in the class or wanting to join the class:
 https://forms.gle/u1rktru9nGiLrtxYA   Before completing the survey, you should read the Syllabus and Course Pledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schedule</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/schedule/</guid>
      <description>Class Meetings Mondays and Wednesday, 12:30pm – 1:45pm in Olsson Hall 018.
Office Hours David Evans: Mondays and Wednesdays, after class until 2:55pm in Rice 507 (or other locations on the way from class). To meet at another time, use https://davidevans.youcanbook.me/ to schedule a time.
Hyun Jae Cho: Mondays, 2-3PM in Rice 442.
Anshuman Suri: Fridays, 12-1PM in Rice 442.
Projects These deadlines and the topics are likely to change (but will be updated when projects are assigned).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>This syllabus is a &amp;ldquo;semi-living document&amp;rdquo; (i.e., more like a virus than a bacterium) subject to change as we adapt during the semester. The course website is managed through a public github repository, so you can see past versions and changes there.
The version as posted on the first day of class is here.
Overview Course Description: This course will look at connections between computing and biology, with a focus on DNA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Course Slack</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/slack/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/slack/</guid>
      <description>You can join the course slack (with any @virginia.edu email address) by visiting: https://join.slack.com/t/computingbiology/signup.
We won&amp;rsquo;t expect students to be on the course slack until the first class (Wednesday, Jan 19 at 12:30pm), but feel free to join early!
(If you want to join but don&amp;rsquo;t have an @virginia.edu email address, contact the course instructor.)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Science Background</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/computer-science-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/computer-science-background/</guid>
      <description>Here is a guide to the computing theory background expected for students entering this course.
If you&amp;rsquo;ve completed cs2150 and a good Theory of Computation or Algorithms course (the official pre-requisites for this course) and remember the big ideas from that class, this should all be familiar to you already, but it may still be useful to refresh your understanding using these materials.
If you haven&amp;rsquo;t taken the prerequisite courses and are getting up to speed on your own, we hope these materials will be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cost of Computation</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/complexity/</guid>
      <description>When we consider the power of our computing models, we have been concerned with understanding what functions can be computed (in theory, which means without any arbitrary limits on their execution) by different computing models. When we want to actual compute using physical computers, cost matters.
For concerete computations where we already know the input and have an implementation of the algorithm, we can measure the cost of executing the algorithm by just running it and recording the cost.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Models of Computation</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/models/</guid>
      <description>To reason precisely about what computers can and cannot do, we need abstract models that capture the things we think are important but avoid the complexities of physical objects.
Models and Mathematics The physical world is messy and suffers from arbitrary limits — this applies both to the physical computing devices we use (which always have some probability of failing and can&amp;rsquo;t even do arithmetic correcly) and even more so to biological systems we consider in this class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>https://computingbiology.github.io/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://computingbiology.github.io/welcome/</guid>
      <description>This is the course website for &amp;ldquo;Computational Biology / Biological Computing&amp;rdquo;, a new University of Virginia course targeted to undergraduate computer science students that will be offered for the first time in Spring 2022. Scheduled course meetings are Mondays and Wednesday, 12:30pm – 1:45pm, in Olsson Hall 018, starting on 19 January 2022.
This course will look at connections between computing and biology, with a focus on DNA. It will include computational methods used in biology focusing on how computing can be used to analyze and design DNA, as well as opportunities to use biological substances and ideas to compute.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>